# Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

McGill University - Génome Québec Innovation Centre

✓ rfarouni@gmail.com • ♦ http://rfarouni.github.io/

I am an applied statistician and computational biologist in the subfield of gene regulation with expertise in the probabilistic modeling and statistical analysis of epigenomics, CRISPR genome editing, and single-cell transcriptomics data.

## **Experience**

## Postdoctoral Researcher

McGill University-Génome Québec Innovation Centre

Research Lab of Dr. Najafabadi, Department of Human Genetics

Montreal, Canada 06/2018-Present

Massachusetts General Hospital-Harvard Medical School

Research Lab of Dr. Pinello, Molecular Pathology Unit

Massachusetts, USA 06/2017-05/2018

- The Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard (Affiliated Member)

Research Intern

Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program

Ohio, USA

Research Lab of Dr. Ewy Mathè, The Ohio State University

05/2016-08/2016

### University Teaching Assistant.....

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA 2013-2017

• Graduate Teaching Associate (Statistics)

Served as a Teaching Assistant for three courses:

- Repeated Measures Models
- Covariance Structure Models
- Data Analysis in Psychology

#### **Education**

#### Academic Qualifications

PhD in Quantitative Psychology (i.e. Applied Statistics)

Ohio, USA

The Ohio State University

2015-2017

Dissertation Topic: 'Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States'

#### Master of Science in Mathematical Statistics

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA 2012-2015

#### Master's Degree in Psychometrics

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA 2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modeling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

### Bachelor's Degree in Psychology

The Pennsylvania State University

Pennsylvania, USA 2011-2012

## **Publications**

## Journal Papers (first author/co-author).....

- o **Farouni, R.**, and Najafabadi, H. S. (2019). Statistical modeling, estimation, and remediation of sample index hopping in multiplexed droplet-based single-cell RNA-seq data. (Submitted). BioRxiv preprint available at https://doi.org/10.1101/617225.
- o Clement, K.†, **Farouni, R.**†, Bauer, D. E., and Pinello, L. (2018). Design and analysis of unique molecular identifiers for deep amplicon sequencing. **Bioinformatics**. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty264. Preprint available at https://www.biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2018/03/23/288118.full.pdf
- o Pinello, L.†, **Farouni, R.**†, and Yuan, G-C. (2018). Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. *Bioinformatics*. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty031. Preprint available at https://doi.org/10.101/199067
- o Baskin, E.<sup>†</sup>, **Farouni, R.**<sup>†</sup>, and Mathè, E. (2017). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. *Bioinformatics*. https://doi.org/10.1093/bioinformatics/btx386. Preprint available at http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/14/080564.full.pdf+html

## Journal Papers (middle author).....

- Seruggia, D., Oti, M., Tripathi, P., Canver, M. C., LeBlanc, L., Di Giammartino, D. C., Bullen, M.J., Nefzger C.M., Sun, Y.B.Y., Farouni, R., Polo, J.M., Pinello, L., Apostolou, E., Kim J., Orkin, S.H., and Das, P.P. (2019). TAF5L and TAF6L Maintain Self-Renewal of Embryonic Stem Cells via the MYC Regulatory Network. *Molecular Cell*.
- o Clement K., Rees H., Canver, M.C., Gehrke J. M., **Farouni, R.**, Hsu, J.Y., Cole, M., Liu D.R., Joung J.K., Bauer, D.E., Pinello, L. (2019). CRISPResso2 provides accurate and rapid genome editing sequence analysis. *Nature Biotechnology*.
- Hsu, J. Y., Fulco, C.P., Cole, M., Canver, M.C., Pellin D., Sher, F, Farouni, R., Clement K., Biasco L., Engreitz, J.M., Lander, E.S., Joung J.K., Bauer, D.E., Pinello, L. (2018). CRISPR-SURF: Exploratory and interactive software for analyzing CRISPR-based tiling screens. *Nature Methods*.

#### Consortium Journal Papers (contributor).....

 Grüning, B., Dale, R., Sjödin, A., Rowe, J., Chapman, B. A., Tomkins-Tinch, C. H., The Bioconda Team, and Köster, J.(2018). Bioconda: A sustainable and comprehensive software distribution for the life sciences. *Nature Methods*. (Bioconda team member contributor, ranked 94 in the consortium author list).

Preprints.

Farouni, R. (2017). A Contemporary Overview of Probabilistic Latent Variable Models. arXiv preprint. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08137

#### Dissertation and Thesis.

- o Farouni, R. (2017). Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States. *PhD Dissertation*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send\_file?accession=osu1492189894812539&disposition=inline
- o Farouni, R. (2014). Latent Variable Models of Categorical Responses in the Bayesian and Frequentist Frameworks. *Masters Thesis*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send\_file?accession=osu1412374136&disposition=inline

Conference Presentations

#### Joint Statistical Meetings

**Seattle** 

Poster Presentation

2015

**Poster Title**: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model (available at https://rfarouni.github.io/assets/posters/jsm2015.pdf).

## **Software Development**

- o Haystack: A Python bioinformatics pipeline for the identification of genomic regions of epigenetic variability across different cell-types, cell-type specific cis-regulatory elements, and their associated transcription factors. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/pinellolab/haystack\_bio.
- o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE.

## **Awards and Fellowships**

#### **Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award**

The Ohio State University 2015

The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2015

**Project Proposal**: 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'

#### The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2014

#### University Fellowship

The Ohio State University 2012

### **Technical Skill Set**

- Statistics and Machine Learning
  - **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R* and *Python* depending on computing goals. Familiar with *Julia*.
  - Deep Learning Frameworks: Experienced in using Pytorch, Tensorflow, and Keras.
  - Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan, familiar with Edward.
- o **Bioinformatics Software:** Analysis of next generation sequencing data, R's Bioconductor core packages, Bowtie2, bedtools.
- Cluster and High-Performance Computing: Good knowledge of running bioinformatics analysis pipelines on super-computing clusters.
- Web and Software Development Tools: LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

## **Journal Review Service**

Psychometrika

O Ad Hoc Reviewer 2015

**Psychological Methods** 

<sup>o</sup> Ad Hoc Reviewer 2016

### **Personal Details**

- o Country of Current Residence: Canada
- o Countries of Previous Residence: USA, Russia, Jordan
- o Interests and Hobbies: Theoretical Linguistics, Evolutionary Biology, Experimental Music
- Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, French (intermediate), Spanish (intermediate)